Register of the John W. Nason Papers, 1921-2001
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1929-1988. (Box 25-38)
  - Council on Foundations (Box 33., Folder 1-15)
  - Council on Foundations (Box 34., Folder 1-2)
  - Danforth Foundation. Memoranda, reports, correspondence, minutes, and printed material, 1963-1973 (Folder 3)
  - Esso Education Founation. Correspondence, pamphlets, and miscellany, 1964-1969 (Folder 4)
  - Estes Park Forum. Correspondence, memoranda, agenda, and minutes, 1970-1972 (Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation. Correspondence (with McGeorge Bundy and others), and memoranda, 1973-1976 (Folder 6)
  - Foreign Policy Association. Correspondence, notes, reports, policy statements, printed material, and miscellany, 1953-1986 (Folder 7-10)
  - Foundation Managers, Inc. Correspondence and report, 1977 (Box 35., Folder 1)
  - Harvard University, Institute for Educational Management. Correspondence, printed material, minutes, and a certificate, 1975-1977 (Folder 2)
  - Harvard University Visiting Committee. Correspondence, schedules, procedures, and miscellany, 1979-1982 (Folder 3)
  - Huntington College. Correspondence and notes, 1984 (Folder 4)
  - International Standing Conference on Philanthropy. Correspondence and printed material, 1983-1987 (Folder 5)
  - Japanese-American relocation during World War II
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Printed Matter
      - General (newspaper clippings and reprints)
      - American Friends Service Committee
        - "The Japanese Evacuation." n.d.
        - "The Japanese Evacuation." Friends Intelligencer1942 July 4. Pamphlet.
      - Balderston, Walter, "The Japanese on the Pacific Coast." Friends Intelligence r, 1942 April 11. Printed copy.
      - Bodine, Thomas R., "The Japanese Displacement." Friends Intelligencer, 1942 June 6. Printed copy.
      - Brethren Service Committee, "Relocation Through the Brethren Hostel." n.d. Pamphlet.
      - Colorado Council of Churches, "The Japanese in our Midst," 1943. Pamphlet.
      - Council for Social Action of the Congregational Christian Churches, "A Touchstone of Democracy: The Japanese in America," 1942 June. Pamphlet.
      - Fellowship of Reconciliation, "American Refugees," 1942 May. Pamphlet.
      - Grew, Joseph C. (Former U.S. Ambassador to Japan), "The Japanese are Tough," 1942 August 30. Transcript of radio address.
      - National Japanese-American Student Relocation Council
        - "Japanese Student Relocation," 1942 August. Pamphlet.
        - "Japanese American Student Relocation: An American Challenge," 1943 March. Revision of preceding, includes rough draft and correspondence.
        - "Directory of American Students of Japanese Ancestry in the Higher Schools, Colleges and Universities of the United States of America," 1943 June. Pamphlet.
        - "How to Help Japanese American Student Relocation," 1943 Sept. 30. Pamphlet
        - "From Camp to College," 1944-1945. Pamphlet, includes draft material.
      - U.S. Senate, "Segregation of Loyal and Disloyal Japanese in Relocation Centers." Doc. No. 96. 1943 Sept. 14. Report on Senate Resolution 166, includes statements by Franklin D. Roosevelt, memoranda and description of evacuation procedures. Pamphlet
      - War Relocation Authority
        - "The Pertinent Facts About Relocation Centers and Japanese-Americans." n.d. Pamphlet
        - "The War Relocation Work Corps," 1943 May. Pamphlet.
      - World Student Service Fund, "The Story of Japanese-American Student Relocation." n.d. Pamphlet
    - Non-printed Matter (Folder 7)
      - American Assocation of Junior Colleges
        - Wartime Letter # 10, 1942 Oct. 31, includes correspondence
        - Wartime Letter # 29, 1943 Dec. 22
        - Wartime Letter # 34, 1944 March 18
      - American Friends Service Committee
        - Pacific Cable, 1942 Sept. 9. Newsletter
        - Memorandum on Problems Caused by Evacuation Orders Affecting Japanese and Problems of Organization of the AFSC Work on the Pacific Coast, 1942 Oct. 5
      - Committee on National Security and Fair Play, 1942 May 18. Memorandum
      - Committee on Resettlement of Japanese Americans, "Action Handbook." n.d.
      - Fellowship of Reconciliation, Memorandum #2, "F.O.R. and the Japanese-American Resettlement," 1943 Feb. 5
      - Japanese American Citizens League
        - Balance statement, Bulletin 5A, 1943 Dec.
        - Bulletin # 33, 1944 Nov. 14
      - National Intercollegiate Christian Council, National Commission on Christian Social Reconstruction, "Fair Play for American Fellow-Students of Japanese Descent: 'That All May Be One'," 1942-1943
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D., letter to Henry L. Stimson, Secty. of War, 1943 Feb. 1. Typed copy.
      - Department of State, 1943 Nov. 16. Press release
      - Department of War, Provost Marshal General's Office, 1944 Jan. 3. Memorandum regarding Japanese-Americans at restricted educational institutions.
      - War Relocation Authority (Folder 8)
        - General
          - "Relocating Japanese-American Evacuees." n.d.
          - "When You Leave the Relocation Center," 1943
          - List of Centers and Offices (2)
          - Student Relocation Newssheet
        - Annotated Bibliographies
          - 1942 Nov. 7, Part I
          - 1943 Aug. 14, Part III
          - 1946 June 30, Part IV
        - Community Analysis Notes
          - "From a Nisei Who Said 'No'," (#1) 1944 Jan. 15
          - "Engagement and Marriage Customs in a Relocation Center" (#2) 1944 Feb. 29
        - Community Analysis Notes (Contd.)
          - "Biography of a Nisei Celery Farmer from Venice, California," (#6) 1944 Dec. 11
        - Community Analysis Reports
          - "Dealing with Japanese Americans," (#1) 1942 Oct.
          - "Causes of Unrest at Relocation Centers," (#2) 1943 Feb.
          - "Evacuee Resistances to Relocation," (#5) 1943 June
          - "Buddhism in the United States," (#9) 1944 May 15
        - Handbook Inserts (Folder 9)
          - 1944 Nov. 10
          - 1945 Jan. 6
        - Post-Exclusion Bulletins
          - # 2 1945 Jan. 2
          - # 3 1945 Jan. 9
          - # 4 1945 Jan. 13
        - Project Analysis Series
          - "The Significant Factors in Requests for Repatriation and Expatriation," (#16) 1944 April 19
          - "Final Report on the Gila River Relocation Center as of May 02, 1945," (#23) 1945 Sept. 24
        - Press Releases
          - 1942 July 31
          - 1944 March 15
          - 1944 April 15
        - Speech Transcripts
          - 1944 Jan. 21, Dillon S. Myer
          - 1944 March 14, Dillon S. Myer
          - 1944 March 23, Dillon S. Myer
      - Young Men's/Women's Christian Association
        - "America's New Crop of Tumbleweeds." Statement by Harry L. Kingman, General Secretary, n.d.
        - "Are You Working on the Resettlement of Japanese-American Citizens?" 1944 Oct. 30
  - Nisei Student Relocation Commemorative Fund, Inc. Correspondence, statement, press release, a clipping, and miscellany, 1979-1986 (Folder 10)
  - Johnson Foundation. Correspondence, agenda, reports, 1967-1984 (Folder 11-12)
  - Junior Board of Commerce. Correspondence, photograph, and certificate, 1941 (Folder 13)
  - Lake Placid Council on Foreign Policy. Correspondence and seminar material, 1979-1986 (Folder 14-15)
  - Leibniz Society of America. Correspondence, reports, notes, and miscellany, 1929-1980 (Box 36., Folder 1)
  - Lilly Endowment. Correspondence and minutes, 1973-1983 (Folder 2)
  - Louisville Foundation. Correspondence, notes, and printed material, 1981 (Folder 3)
  - Middlebury College. Correspondence, memoranda, and notes, 1980-1983 (Folder 4)
  - Military Service (Folder 5)
    - Conscientious Objectors
      - General
      - NJASRC staff members: Correspondence regarding status and position
        - Beale, Howard
        - Bodine, Thomas R.
        - Emlen, Woodruff J.
        - Stevenson, William C.
        - Wilcher, Denny
    - Japanese-Americans (Folder 6)
      - Printed materials: newspaper articles
      - Non-printed materials
        - Kuroki, Ben, U.S.A.F., 1944 Feb. 4. Speech transcript. Japanese-American Citizens League Bulletin #17
        - Wyoming District Court (Judge Kennedy) regarding the violation of the Selective Training and Service Act of 1940 by Japanese-Americans
        - Volunteers for Victory, Topaz, Utah. "Fighting Americans, Too!" 1943 April 3. Small booklet.
        - War Relocation Authority, Project Analysis Series #15, "The Reaction of Heart Mountain to the Opening of Selective Service to the Nisei," 1944 April 1
  - Miner Institute. Correspondence, research proposal, reports, and printed material, 1971-1973 (Folder 14)
  - Museum Roundtable. Agenda and correspondence, 1984 (Folder 15)
  - National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges. Correspondence and notes, 1980 (Folder 16)
  - National Endowment for the Arts. Memorandum and correspondence, 1977 (Folder 17)
  - New England Board of Higher Education. Correspondence, notes, and conference material, 1980 (Folder 18)
  - New Hampshire Charitable Fund. Correspondence and program, 1978-1984 (Folder 19)
  - New Hampshire University System. Correspondence and notes, 1981 (Folder 20)
  - New Jersey Grantmakers. Conference material, 1981 (Folder 21)
  - New Jersey State College. Memorandum, notes, and correspondence, 1976 (Folder 22)
  - New York, State University of. Correspondence, report, and miscellany, 1980 (Folder 23)
  - North Carolina Conference of Trustees. Correspondence and program, 1980 (Folder 24)
  - North Country Community College. Correspondence, by-laws, and minutes, 1971-1981 (Box 37., Folder 1)
  - North Country School. Correspondence and printed material, 1970-1983 (Folder 2)
  - Northern States Power Company. Correspondence, memoranda, and curricula, 1971 (Folder 3)
  - Northwest Area Foundation. Correspondence and memoranda, 1982-1984 (Folder 4)
  - Paul Smith's College. Correspondence, printed material, and by-laws, 980- 1982 (Folder 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa. Correspondence and minutes, 1967-1976 (Folder 6)
  - Phillips Exeter Academy. Correspondence and miscellany, 1972-1986 (Folder 7)
  - Pomona College. Speech and correspondence, 1940-1941 (Folder 8)
  - Quakerism. Notes and miscellany, 1956-1957 (Folder 9)
  - Skidmore College. Notes, miscellany, and correspondence, 1981 (Folder 10)
  - Society for Religion in Higher Education. Speeches, notes, correspondence, miscellany, and newsletters, 1944-1975 (Box 38., Folder 1)
  - Southeastern Council of Foundations. Correspondence, notes, and conference material, 1975-1978 (Folder 2)
  - Swathmore College. Correspondence and miscellany, 1953-1979 (Folder 3)
  - Syracuse University. Correspondence and conference material, 1979 (Folder 4)
  - Texas Association of Colleges and Universities. Correspondence and conference material, 1983 (Folder 5)
  - Thomas J. Watson Foundation. Correspondence and miscellany, 1970-1973 (Folder 6)
  - Un-American Activities Committee (Dies Committee), U.S. House of Representatives (Folder 7)
    - Japanese American Citizens League, "The Dies Committee, the Hearst Press, and Their Japanese Nightmares," 1943 Summer. Includes memorandum.
    - War Relocation Authority
      - Comments on press reports of testimony. 1943 May-June
      - Comments on remarks of Rep. John M. Costello, Chairman, House subcommittee, 1943 June 28
      - Statement on testimony of Harold H. Townsend before Costello subcommittee on May 26, 1943. 1943 July 7
      - Myer, Dillon S., Statements before Costello subcommittee. 1943 July 6-7
  - United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia. Conference material, 1966 (Folder 8)
- Audiovisual File, c. 1921-1987., (29 prints / 1 envelope (10.A-V 83003)
  9 prints of John Nason, circa 1921-1962; 1 print of Mr. and Mrs. Nason, 1962; 5 prints of a dinner of the Nisei Student Relocation Commemorative Fund, Inc., 1982; 4 prints of a university centennial celebration, 1951; 5 prints of the 60th anniversary dinner of the Foreign Policy Association, 1977; and 5 prints of various meetings or groups, 1967-1987
- Incremental materials (Box 39-51)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.